PETER STONE: Thanks,
Dawn, for inviting me.
and thanks to all of
you for being here.
It's a pleasure
to be joining you.
So what I'm going to do in
this session in this talk is,
as advertised by the title,
I'm going to talk about my view
of autonomous agents, and
in particular a broad view,
not just the latest
incarnation of, quote,
"agentic artificial intelligence
or agentic large language
models," but really the roots of
the term autonomous agents with
emphasis on embodiment,
interaction, and learning.
And what I mean by
embodiment is really robots.
I know I looked
through the topics that
have been covered so
far this semester,
and there's been a
bunch on learning
and a bunch on interaction.
So you had from Noam Brown, you
heard about multi-agent systems.
And also I think
your last session
was on multi-agent systems
and also a lot on learning
and scientific discovery.
But I think there's been
less coverage so far
of the embodiment side, which
sometimes is physical robots,
sometimes simulated robots.
And so I'm going to
place an emphasis there.
I'm going to start by giving
a broad overview of where I'm
coming from, the kind of
research I do in my lab,
and so tell you about a
lot of things very briefly,
so almost nothing about
a whole bunch of things.
But then I'll do a deeper
dive on one or two things,
depending on how
much time we have,
that go into more of
the technical details.
And of course, there's more
information on my web page
and my papers about
all the things
I'm going to talk about here.
And you're always
welcome to reach out
if you have questions
about things
that I only touch on briefly.
So first, I'm going to just
talk about what my view is.
And I'm jumping between a bunch
of different slide decks here.
So apologies if it's
not one unified view.
Hopefully things will
go smoothly enough.
But my view of agents,
autonomous agents
have been a focus of
study in the field
of artificial intelligence
for a long time,
for at least three decades,
actually, more than that.
I've been involved in the
field for around three decades.
And so much longer than this
year's buzzword of agentic AI.
But what is-- fundamentally,
what is an agent?
My view is, very simply, an
agent is an intelligent system
that interacts with
the environment
through sensors and effectors,
as shown in the diagram here.
I mean, you could ask the
question, is a chatbot an agent?
Usually, we think of an
autonomous agent as one
where there's not necessarily
an input-output sequence
and then it sort of
waits for more input,
but rather more of a
continuous loop where there's
sensors coming in
from the environment,
or sensations coming in from
the environment, actions
that are taken that
affect the next sensations
but you don't have to wait
to be called or invoked.
And so there are
software agents.
There are also physical
or embodied agents, which
usually go by the term robot.
The first slide was
a modified slide
from a definition
in a term when I--
or a class when I teach
robotics in the first session,
I usually ask what is a robot.
And it's almost the
same definition.
It's a robot is an
intelligent system that
interacts with the
physical environment
through sensors and effectors.
So the only word I've added
here is the word physical.
But otherwise, so all
robots are agents,
not all agents are robots.
And then we often
think about what's
an intelligent complete robot,
or you could substitute the word
agent here, an
intelligent complete agent
is one that has some cognition,
the intelligence aspect.
So it gets the sensations,
it has the actions.
And there's the raw sensors
and the raw actuators,
which if it's a
robot, you can think
of as being the
cameras and the motors.
But then there's the intelligent
part shown in green here,
which is the sensing and
modeling the world based
on the raw sensor perceptions,
sensor readings, that
is the perception module.
On the other side,
the far other side,
there's the action
aspect, which is,
once you've decided
what you want to do,
how do you actually do it?
And then translate that
into the motor commands,
the low-level actuators.
And in between is what
many people consider
the brains of the
system or the cognition
where you're deciding
what actions to take.
And that could be
through planning,
through multi-agent
coordination, teamwork,
opponent modeling or
teammate modeling, et cetera.
So all of my research takes
this view of what an agent is.
And I just wanted to frame that
in the context of this talk
because I think--
like I said, nowadays,
there's some people take
a more narrow view
of what an agent is
or an agentic system is, but
really it's quite a broad term
and broadly encompassing.
So as I said, and I'm going
to start by telling you almost
nothing about a lot of things.
And starting from
where I'm coming from,
I am here at UT
Austin, where there's
a lot of exciting
things happening.
We were awarded one of the first
National Science Foundation AI
institutes, the Institute for
Foundations of Machine Learning.
This is an organization that
spawned the Machine Learning
Lab that's headed by Adam
Klivans and Sanjay Shakkottai.
We also have an ethical
AI system on campus
that's inspired by the One
Hundred Year Study of AI
that I've been a leader in.
But the one on campus here
at UT is called Good Systems,
and it involves people from
many different disciplines
and the ethical AI initiative.
I was the founding
director of Texas Robotics.
We have a beautiful new space.
We're going to be hosting--
this is before we
filled it with robots,
it's an old gymnasium that's
now filled with robots
from across campus--
we're going to be
hosting the conference
on robot learning here in
about a year next November.
So I hope many of you will
have a chance to come on campus
and see that.
And there's also a lot of
innovative AI education going on
here.
We have an online AI master's
program at a price point
of $10,000.
We have created an AI literacy
course for the entire campus
with all of the
materials online.
So these are all things that
I'd be happy to talk about
in much more detail.
But from the perspective of
my own research in the things
I'm going to talk
to you about today,
the unifying question
that's held together,
all of the different things
that go on in my lab,
and have over the past
several decades, is this,
it's what degree can
autonomous, intelligent agents
learn in the
presence of teammates
and/or adversaries in
real-time dynamic domains?
And I'll emphasize,
again, this question
was the core question of
my PhD thesis back in 1998
and has appeared in almost every
talk I've given since then.
And it has included
this term agent.
So that's a way of emphasizing
that this is not a new term.
It's not a new
buzzword, but really
something that's been
around for a very
long time in the community.
This question causes
us to focus in my group
on publishing in several
different subareas of AI
autonomous agents,
multi-agent systems, robotics,
machine learning, especially
reinforcement learning.
And we do both foundational
bottom-up research
and more use-inspired research.
And when I give a
one-slide introduction
to things that go
on in my lab, it's
a lot easier to talk about those
use-inspired or the use cases
that motivate the research.
So one has been that
I focused on a lot
and found inspiring
is robot soccer.
So here's some of the
old Sony AIBO robots.
This is a video from
probably almost 20 years ago
of the robots sensing, deciding,
and acting no remote control
from the RoboCup, or
robot soccer competitions.
We've now moved towards
humanoid robots.
So this is a clip from also a
competition several years ago,
where we were playing a team
from the University of Bremen.
Our robots are the ones with
their hands behind their backs
and pink waistbands.
And again, remember that
they're fully autonomous.
They're sensing, deciding,
and acting like an agent does.
This is a multi-agent system.
So there's several robots
cooperating together.
Here, you see a robot
going in on a breakaway,
and it'll end up scoring a goal.
And we went on to win this game
and winning the competition
that year.
And there's all kinds
of agent challenges
that come up in this
kind of a setting.
The goal of RoboCup, the
Robot Soccer World Cup,
is to create a team
of humanoid robots
that can beat the best World Cup
champion on a real soccer field
by the year 2050.
And so this is an
ambitious goal,
but it's sort of in
that line of AI systems
that have done better than the
best humans at various tasks,
from chess to go, to poker.
You heard about, I think,
about StarCraft in this course
already.
And I'll talk about
another one as we go,
but soccer would be taking it
to the next level in many ways.
And if you watch that
video, you might be saying,
oh, well, that's not even
close to human level.
The robots are still not
close to human level,
but there's been big leaps.
So that's roughly what it
looked like at the competition
two years ago.
But in this year's competition,
we had a game of humanoid robots
for the first time with people.
And you'll see me
here with the ball.
And I was playing on the
team with the robots,
because it's still too easy for
the people to beat the robot.
So it was three people
against me and the robots.
And I had no idea what
was going to happen.
The robots didn't
actually even sense me,
but I left the
ball for this robot
here that I'm showing
with my pointer,
and you'll see what happened.
And this was very
unexpected, but shows
you the level at
which we're getting
to now with robot soccer.
So the robot just turned
around and kicked it
between the RoboCup president's
legs, that's Ubbo Visser.
I tried to get the robot to
give me a hi-five afterwards,
it didn't.
But in any case, we're
at this level where--
and we would never have been
able to see that, I think,
even a couple years ago, or even
a couple months ago, let me say.
And so there is a
lot of progress.
And I think it's not completely
out of the other question
that by the year 2050, we would
have humanoid robots playing
at human professional level.
I wouldn't bet my life on it.
I think they're
trying to make systems
like that happen in the real
world, in physical systems
is much harder than
doing it all in software.
But there's been a lot of
progress in the past 25 years
or so.
I'm also inspired by
general-purpose service robots.
If you come to my
lab, you'll often
see robots like
this one just sort
of wandering
through the hallways
in this kind of a setting.
And actually, the
RoboCup competitions
involve general-purpose
service robots as well,
doing things like
acting as a host, having
to pick up items to set the
table, put away groceries.
Here's the task
serving breakfast.
So there's a competition
called RoboCup@Home, trying
to create robots that are
generally capable in this way,
and that's been very inspiring
to my research as well.
And then, like many, I've been
inspired by autonomous driving.
An autonomous car is an agent.
It has to sense,
decide, and act.
I had a car in the DARPA Urban
Challenge, the one pictured
here.
I don't have that car anymore.
As you know the car companies
and companies like Waymo
and Zoox are putting
a lot of money
into making this a reality.
But we've thought
over the course
of several years, and
actually a couple decades now,
what the world would look like
when all the cars on the road
are autonomous?
Would we still need traffic
signals and stop signs,
or will we be able to see
systems more like this?
This was the basis for
Dresdner's thesis back in,
might have been 2010 or so.
But this video, I think,
came out first in 2004.
And what's happening
is that each car
is an agent calling
ahead for a reservation
through the intersection.
And once it turns white,
it has a guaranteed path
through the intersection
that won't interfere
with any of the other cars.
When they're yellow, they
don't have a reservation yet,
so they often have to stop.
But this is when all
the cars are autonomous.
We may be able to see
intersections like that.
We've also looked
at what happens
if you have human drivers
mixed with autonomous drivers
and things like that.
And so I could give a whole
talk on any of these topics.
Most recently, I
mentioned that I've
been inspired by these
challenges of trying
to get AI agents to be better
than humans at various tasks.
And so with my group at Sony AI,
we actually, a couple of years
ago, contributed to
that stream of results.
We had a paper on
the cover of Nature,
where we created
reinforcement learning agents
that were able to drive faster
than the very best human drivers
at the game, Gran Turismo, which
is a very physically realistic
simulation environment.
So this was the first
time-- the reason
it was picked up
by Nature, this was
the first time
that AI agents were
better than humans at a
real-time control task, not
turn-taking like poker and chess
and go and things like that,
or I should say a physically
realistic real-time control
task.
And the one way to
get a sense of that
is to watch above and below, an
expert human driver, Ken Chan,
driving in the simulator in
the top half of the screen
and in the real car on the
bottom half of the screen, where
he's controlling the same car on
the same track in the simulator
versus in the real world.
And it models sufficiently
the slip stream and tire
slip and traction
and things like that,
so that he was able to finish
the driving at his best in both
the real world
and the simulator.
He finished the lap within a
10th of a second of the times
in the two modalities.
And there are people who have
trained in this simulator
to become professional
race car drivers.
And so we did a race against
four of the best human drivers.
This was in October of 20-- we
first raced them in July of 2021
and did not win--
the humans were still
better than the AI agents.
But then by October of
2021, there was an event
that's the basis for the Nature
article from February of 2022,
where we beat the four of
the best drivers in the world
who've put in their 10,000 hours
to become real experts on three
different race car
track combinations.
And since then, it's actually
been deployed in the video game.
If you have a PlayStation
and the game Gran Turismo,
you can race against GT Sophy.
There's been a lot of
research beyond the paper
to make it more
engaging and fun.
But fundamentally, this
was a success story
for end-to-end reinforcement
learning, where
the agent started acting
randomly, literally just driving
in circles or backwards or off
the track, crashing into things
and getting reward for
moving fast around the track.
And after about
a day of training
on a bank of
PlayStations, it was
able to do better than the
best humans on an empty track,
and after about a week,
better than the best
humans in a competitive racing
scenario, where it learns skills
like this one, where the colored
car is the agent GT Sophy,
the white ones are
all human drivers.
And here you see it learning to
take a defensive line, so it's
not going the fastest
it can around the track,
but rather positioning
itself in such a way
that it's hard for
the humans to pass it.
And it's learned to do
that entirely on its own.
So this is work from a large
team of people at Sony.
And like I said, it's
ongoing, and it's something
that we're really proud of.
Most recently, with a different
team at Sony AI, in fact,
very recently, this
is just last week,
or maybe within the last two
weeks that this was published
in Nature, we contributed a new
human-centric image benchmark
for--
basically, as I said
here in the tagline,
and this was led
by Alice Xiang It's
the first globally diverse,
consensually collected fairness
evaluation data set
for a wide variety
of human-centric
computer vision tasks.
So really what sets
it apart, our goals
were to identify the
ethical and legal issues
of creating data sets,
rather than just scraping
YouTube and Instagram and Reddit
and things that go into training
these large models.
Our goal was to try to, at least
at the scale that you could
for evaluation, create
a data set where
all of the participants,
everybody who appears
in the pictures,
has been compensated
and has self-identified
what the label should
be that describe them.
And so tried to
start with FHIBE,
tried to establish an industry
standard for AI ethics.
And also, it's built
ethically, but also
to evaluate bias in AI models.
And so in a way of
creating, and I'm not
going to read through
the slide here,
but you can see some of
the features of FHIBE.
And it comprises 10,000 images.
So it's not enough
to train a model on,
but it's enough to evaluate
a model for biases.
It's the first one that
goes across the whole global
geography, 81
countries and areas,
and categorizes a whole
bunch of different features,
as you can see here.
And annotations of the
camera that are used,
the environment,
and the features
of the people in
the image itself,
as labeled by the
person who appears
in the image in many cases.
And so we use this in
the Nature article, which
you can find online
now do analysis
of the sorts of biases that
happen in visual language
models.
And I verified some existing
ones that were known
and also identified
some new ones.
So that's, in a nutshell, the
kinds of things that inspire me
and the research that I do have.
As I said, you have--
another theme that I think
comes up a lot in agents,
and you've heard a little bit
about during this semester,
is human-in-the-loop learning,
which is learning from
interaction.
And there's a system
that was developed
by a former student of mine,
Brad Knox, who's now faculty
here at UT Austin, that was a
system called TAMER, Teaching
an Agent Manually via
Evaluative Reinforcement.
And the idea here, it was
the-- actually, I think,
it has a claim to
being the first system
to do reinforcement learning
from human feedback,
or RLHF, which is a key point, a
key aspect of training language
models now.
But his core demonstration
was in the game of Tetris
that you see here.
Most of you are probably
familiar-- you're
trying to clear rows.
And what's happening
in the top-left corner,
a person is saying, good move
or bad move-- green for good,
and red for bad.
And at first, it was random.
This was a task that at
the time of the system,
you could do with
reinforcement learning
if you trained for hundreds
of thousands of games.
But Brad was able to show
that even in the first game,
with this human
feedback, you can start
doing much better than random.
So it's already starting
to clear some lines.
Oops.
And then by the third
game, it's able to--
so this is after just
two games of a person--
two episodes of a person
providing positive and negative
feedback.
It's already able to
clear hundreds of lines.
And so this was one of the
early examples or demonstrations
of the power of learning
from human interaction,
as opposed to just
random exploration.
GT Sophy was purely
from random exploration.
It was all
reinforcement learning.
This is reinforcement
learning from human feedback.
And one of the key
lessons here was
that TAMER learns more
quickly than autonomous
learning from straight
reinforcement learning.
It doesn't take hundreds
of thousands of games.
It takes three games to
get to quite a good level,
but ultimately
doesn't do as well
as if you allow
for reinforcement
learning to learn from scratch.
You may have heard of the
bitter lesson from Rich Sutton
that injecting human
input could bring down
the ultimate performance.
But there are also
ways of combining them.
So we had an award-winning
paper TAMER plus RL,
which learned both from human
feedback and autonomously.
And this was also with Brad
Knox, part of his thesis.
Then collaborating with Garrett
Warnell, pictured on the right,
we had an extension to
video or image input,
a system called Deep Tamer.
And like I said, this
really was, I think,
the first example of RLHF,
which has really been
super impactful lately.
And then this has been
extended to also learning,
not just from explicit
feedback but learning
from implicit feedback.
So not just a person explicitly
saying good move or bad move,
but you can imagine if
you were an autonomous car
and your passengers
looked like this,
you wouldn't need
somebody to tell
you-- shouldn't need somebody
to tell you that you've
done something wrong.
You've scared them.
And so this should allow you to
learn from implicit feedback.
So we, a couple years
ago, in a coral paper,
introduced a system called
EMPATHIC, for Evaluative MaPping
for Effective Task-learning
via Human Implicit Cues,
but it's about learning from
implicit human feedback.
And then we've gone on to think
about all the different ways in,
or many of the different ways,
in which humans can provide
input in machine learning
through the robot navigation
problem, where a robot
has to start at a point
and get to a global goal
while avoiding obstacles.
I'm not going to go into
the details on this again,
I'm just going to show
you the punch line where
we were-- but it's trying
to learn to have the robots
move through very
constrained spaces, which
is not a solved problem yet.
So it's navigation, is pretty
well known how to do it.
But if you're trying to navigate
through very constrained spaces
that are not much
bigger than the robot,
there are navigation
packages out there--
oops, I wanted to go to
the previous slide here.
Yeah, there's navigation
packages out there,
but they require lots of opaque
parameters, things like this,
that you wouldn't
really know how to tune,
if you wanted the
robot to work well.
And they're different in
very different settings,
whether the robot's in a
corridor or an open space
or an obstacle
course or a pinch.
And so right now, if
you want to get a robot
to navigate effectively
in these kinds of spaces,
it takes a roboticist to
fine-tune those planning
parameters, or at least it did.
And so we explored various
ways of using human input
to allow for a robot to
learn how to do this.
So ranging from a teleoperated
demonstration where a person is
literally just
remote-controlling the robot,
and then we have the robot
explore in parameter space
to come up with
the parameters that
would lead to the most similar
behavior to the slightly less
demanding corrective information
or interventions where
a person doesn't need to always
be remote-controlling the robot,
but can just step in when the
robot is doing something wrong.
And again, now the robot can
try to emulate or predict
when a person would
step in to intervene.
We had a system for doing it
from evaluative feedback, which
is much closer to the TAMER
system, where the person just
has to say good
move or bad move,
give positive and
negative feedback,
all the way up to
reinforcement learning systems.
And so you can also
find a full talk
on my website about the various
different technical algorithms
behind doing this
Adaptive Planner Parameter
Learning, where
rather than learning
all of the different parameters
of a navigation stack,
we're instead treating
that navigation stack
like a black box and learning
just the parameters that
will lead to the
behavior that you want.
And so the way I think of
this is in the language
of machine learning.
We're learning a
parameter policy.
Rather than outputting
the raw actions,
we're outputting the
parameters to a navigation
stack or a classical
motion planner,
and trying to learn which
ones lead to the actions
that you most desire.
I think that's where
I'll stop in terms
of telling you almost nothing
about a lot of different things.
Like I said, when I
looked through the topics
that you've covered so
far, there have been,
I think, less on the
physical robots than
on the multi-agent systems
and the reinforcement
learning that I
focused on a lot.
Oh, actually, sorry,
I take that back.
There was one more thing I
wanted to tell you almost
nothing about, which is,
on the interaction side,
a problem that's fascinated
me over the past,
decade-and-a-half or so,
called ad hoc teamwork,
which is a particular
type of interaction,
where the goal is to try to
create an individual agent that
is good at cooperating
with teammates,
but you don't necessarily
get to, or you don't at all,
get to control who
those teammates are.
The kind of thing that
people can really do well
when they're playing pick-up
soccer or pick-up basketball,
but now we want robots to
be able to do if there were
a disaster-rescue scenario
and lots of different people
brought the robots
together, we don't
want to have to reprogram
them to work as a team.
We want them to be able to
figure out on-the-fly how
to be able to work together.
And so there's a bunch
of work in my lab
also on this problem of creating
a good team player, which
is, I think, a part of the
multi-agent systems challenge
or the interaction challenge.
And there's a challenge
paper from AAAI 2010
that introduces ad hoc
teamwork as a problem.
And then there's been a
bunch of theoretical research
and experimental
research on the topic.
OK, now, I really do--
that's the whirlwind
part of this talk, where
I've told you very little about
a lot of work that pertains
to machine learning,
especially reinforcement
learning, and
interaction, especially
ad hoc teamwork,
multi-agent systems.
But you've seen some coverage of
those in the semester already.
With regards to
embodiment, I'm going
to take a little
bit of a deeper dive
and show you a paper from just--
it was presented at CoRL just
about a month ago.
And let me put this
into full-screen mode.
Why is this not working?
Try it again.
And this is the goal of--
I'm sorry, this
should be coming up.
It's the goal of trying to
do reinforcement learning--
so there we go--
in the real world.
So the motivation here is, and
I should say this is the PhD
thesis work of Jiaheng
Hu, shown here,
and he's co-advised by myself
and Roberto Martín-Martin.
And this paper was
published, like I
said at CoRL, the Conference
on Robot Learning recently.
And so the paper is SLAC, for
Simulation-Pretrained Latent
Action Space for Whole
Body Real-World RL.
And so the key here is
trying to do real-world RL.
I want to get rid of
that little thing there.
No, that's not
what I want to do.
I'm sorry.
This is not going
exactly how I was hoping.
Let's just keep it in this mode.
So it's learning visuo-motor,
contact-rich, whole-body mobile
manipulation with real-world
reinforcement learning
without a single demonstration.
So when you're doing
learning in robotics,
you can't do what we
did with GT Sophy, which
was learn on a bank
of PlayStations,
hundreds of thousands or
millions of interactions.
While we were all sleeping,
the computers would be working.
When you're working
on a real robot,
you have to work
very, very efficiently
with very little data.
And so you have to
learn very efficiently.
And a motivating
task here is we want
to do whole-body
mobile manipulation.
So this is a task such
as wiping the blue off
of the whiteboard while avoiding
the obstacle of this trash band.
And so it requires
the robot to know
how to move to avoid
obstacles and not just to--
the standard way to do this
with reinforcement learning
would be to just explore lots
and lots of random actions
first.
And you can do that if
you have a simulator.
But it's costly to build
high-fidelity simulators.
It's sometimes infeasible to
build a simulator that simulates
your robot well enough that if
you just learn in simulation
and apply the policy in the
real world, it would just work.
There have been some
successes of that,
it's not always straightforward.
And so, we want to try to
learn without the benefit
of the learning happening
in the simulator.
One way people often
get around that is
through imitation learning
or some kind of learning
from human feedback, as I
showed with the adaptive planner
parameter learning.
But that can be very
costly to collect
and the high quality
demonstrations.
So our goal is to do real-world
reinforcement learning
with directly learning
from real interactions
without this high-fidelity
simulation or demonstrations.
And so, like I said, if you just
use a standard state-of-the-art
reinforcement learning method,
you're going to just flail.
So if you're trying to
learn to wipe the blue mark
and you're getting reward
for wiping the blue mark,
and you're just
sending random commands
to all the motors of the
robot moving the base around,
randomly moving the
arm around randomly,
you're not going
to get very far.
It's going to probably the
battery's going to die,
or you're going to lose
patience before it learns
to do anything correctly.
And so there's a huge
challenge for trying
to learn with sufficient
sample efficiency and safety
in the real world.
And so the system that Jiaheng
came up with is, like I said,
it's called SLAC.
And the key here is that
we need a good action
space to facilitate
sample efficiency
and safety in the real world.
If we have, rather than sending
raw commands to the robot,
but have a much more
abstract action space,
then there's much
less to explore,
and we're going to use
a low-fidelity simulator
to come up with that
latent action space.
So we're going to assume that
it's not that hard to come up
with a rough simulator
of the robot,
and that we can
then use that to--
so here's a picture of what a
low-fidelity simulator might
look like.
So it's sort of
models the robot,
but it's not going
to be perfect.
And we want to use what's known
as unsupervised reinforcement
learning to learn
task-agnostic behaviors
in a low-fidelity simulator.
So what do I mean by
unsupervised reinforcement
learning?
That means giving
a robot or an agent
an environment to explore in,
but no reward signal, no task.
So it's unsupervised because
there's no reward signal,
and get it to try to just
figure out all of the actions
that it might want to
take, that might be useful
when it is given a reward
function downstream
in the future.
So the kind of thing where
we put a baby in a playpen--
a human baby in a
playpen, they tend
to try stacking blocks
up or squeezing things
to see what noise they make.
They don't really
have any task to do,
but they're, in
some sense, training
themselves to do things
that might be useful
once they are given tasks.
And so that's the
idea, is trying
to get a robot to do
the same sort of thing.
That's what the unsupervised
reinforcement learning idea is.
And the goal here is to come
up with the types of actions
that you might
want a robot to do.
And so what we're trying
to learn is a latent action
space where you give just--
you define a number
of dimensions,
some small set of
dimensions, and then
try to make it so that when
you change the latent actions,
you get meaningfully different
behaviors in the real world
so that this latent
action space can create--
you might imagine
that the robot would
learn to get close to the
whiteboard versus getting
far away from the whiteboard.
Those are something
that you can do
by just moving the
base of the robot,
or you could imagine
another action
dimension controlling the arm
or where the camera is pointing.
And so we came up with
a method called DUSD,
or disentangled unsupervised
skill discovery,
and this was before
the SLAC paper, that
does learn this sort of diverse,
temporally extended behaviors
by trying to come up with--
by maximizing or minimizing
the mutual information
between the behaviors
you get when you change
the latent action features.
There's been previous work.
There was a paper called
Diversity is All You Need,
or DIAYN, from Sergey
Levine's group that
had that insight initially.
But one of the
things we added is
that we tried to do it
in a disentangled way.
So to create a
structured action space,
by which we mean that if you
vary one latent variable,
it only changes one
dimension of the action space
and also adds safety.
So what I mean by that is we
want to add two different reward
signals.
One is such that if you change
one of the latent action
features, it only changes one
aspect of the robot's behavior.
So here the red indicates
where the camera is pointing
and the blue indicates
where the arm is moving
and the red indicates
where the bass is moving.
We wanted sort of a nice
structured action space
so that you can--
if you vary one of
the latent action
features and hold
the others constant,
it'll only move the base,
the arm of the camera.
And so that was
something that we
were able to do using DUSD,
using what we call the skill
empowerment reward.
And then we also added a
hand-coded safety reward
that's like don't collide with
yourself, something like that.
And when you put those together,
you can come up with a--
train the action decoder in
this and the latent actions
such that you get this
structured and safe set
of actions in the
low-fidelity simulator.
And then once you have that
in the second step of SLAC,
you can then take the
learned latent action space
and use it for downstream task
learning in the real world.
And so, again, you have this
lower dimensional action space
where each dimension changes the
different aspect of the robot.
And so then we're going
to separately develop
a factorized version
of Soft Actor-Critic.
Soft Actor-Critic is one of the
popular reinforcement learning
algorithms.
It's actually the basis for the
one that we used in GT Sophy
as well.
And it leverages the structure
of the latent action space.
And so what I mean
by that is that once
you're given a reward, once you
know what your reward terms are,
you might have a reward for
where the robot is located
that can be controlled
by where the base is,
a reward for where the robot is
looking that can be controlled
by where the camera is pointing,
a reward for what you're
picking up or touching, which is
controlled by where the arm is.
The idea is that not
every latent factor
controls every reward term.
So you can get a much
sparser and more accurate
prediction of the value function
in reinforcement learning terms,
if you can learn to separate
which action factors control
which reward terms.
And so we did this in a paper
that appeared at RSS 2023.
We used a conditional
mutual information metric
that allows us to say, well,
if I change a particular action
dimension, how does it change
the reward factors that I get.
And so you can learn
a masking matrix
that says, if you want to-- if
you have a reward term that only
depends on where the base of the
robot is, which action factors
do you need to vary, or can
you vary to get that reward,
and so on for
every other factor.
I know I'm going quickly here
from a technical perspective.
I'm not going through
all of the math,
but you can find this
in the papers that
are referenced on the slide.
And so then we can
use all the data
that's used to infer which
action factors affect which
reward terms for learning.
And I'll get to the punchline
and the video demonstrations
here coming up.
We can take some
real-world tasks
and then do learning entirely
from the onboard observations
from the robot's camera
and proprioception, which
is where the joint angles
are at any given time.
And now learn a
task policy, the one
that actually gets rewards for
the task, like in this case,
it's sweeping
something into a basket
with your frozen pre-trained
latent action model, which
is what you use the
low-fidelity simulation for it
to come up with this
structured action space.
And then if the action space
is low-dimensional enough,
you can actually learn to
control the various reward
factors, where to look,
where to move your hand,
where to move the base by
exploiting that causal matrix
from the previous slide that
allows you to change the various
action factors to
get the various--
to maximize the
various reward terms.
And then here's a demonstration.
So at the start of
training, a robot
has no idea how
to solve its task,
just like in the previous
video I showed you.
So it's sort of moving
around randomly.
So here's the first minute or
so of training minute or two.
But after only 40 minutes,
so it gets a behavior now
where we've given
it reward for being
able to successfully wipe off
the blue marks from the board.
And it's learned to successfully
move the base, the camera,
and the arm in unison to be
able to achieve that task.
And again, with
all of the starting
from random behavior and 40
minutes later having learned
this skill.
But by leveraging this
very efficient action space
that was learned in simulation.
Using exactly the
same methodology,
we can end that same
latent action space.
It can learn to sweep garbage
onto a tray or garbage
into a bag.
And also it can learn
to wipe the whiteboard
with or without an
obstacle in front of it.
And so we've done these
four different tasks
that I just mentioned.
And compared to doing all of
the learning in simulation
or a couple of existing
methods, one that which
learns entirely in the
low-level action space
rather than in this more
factorized abstract action
space.
Also another method called RLPD.
And we both have
higher success rate
at those four tasks,
and importantly,
fewer safety violations
during learning
so that the robot can actually
do this learning efficiently
in the real world.
And in all cases, all of
those policies trained
in less than one hour
on the real robots
so that we end up with
an autonomous agent
that's able to
learn in that case.
So you can learn a lot more
details from the paper.
And this is a theme for a lot
of the recent research in my lab
is trying to use
simulation, but to allow
for learning in the real
world, but not necessarily
by just learning
all in simulation
and transferring
the policy directly,
but instead leveraging the
simulation in more creative ways
like here to pre-train an
efficient action space.
And of course, like
many, we've also
been exploring how can
we use foundation models,
large language models and
visual language models
to not necessarily control the
low-level actions of the robot,
but to provide some
of the common sense
knowledge for the robot.
So that's what I wanted to do
in terms of the embodiment, sort
of a somewhat deep dive
into a particular research
paper on embodiment.
I think I have time to also go
in a little bit of a deep dive
on GT Sophy as well.
So I've given you
an overview of this.
Oops, where is it?
Oh, I think I have it here.
There we go.
So I've given you an
introduction to GT Sophy,
but I'm going to tell you a
little bit more about it now
and then I'll pause
for questions.
So again, to remind
you, this is the work
that was done at Sony AI on
racing champion Gran Turismo
drivers with deep
reinforcement learning.
So this is going to
that other extreme
where we now do
have a simulation.
And actually the whole task is
to do well in the simulation.
So this is not
embodiment anymore.
This is to build a real
world-class world-expert agent
at race car driving.
And I showed you
this slide already.
But the success was just like
in the success cases of chess
and poker and Go, it relied on
a great compute architecture.
There was a lot of data that
went in, a lot of engineering.
It wasn't just sort of a new
out-of-the-blue principle.
So there's a lot of data
and top-notch engineering
and compute.
But there also were a few
algorithmic and methodological
insights that went into
making it possible.
And I'll try to give you a
sense of those right now.
Those are what are
featured in the article.
Just as a reminder, in
every video, I show you,
the colored cars are
going to be GT Sophy
and the white ones
are controlled
by one of the very best
drivers at GT Sophy.
I've already told you
about the simulator itself
and that we do this with
reinforcement learning.
The main challenges
that made this
more difficult
than previous tasks
was that it's real-time control.
So we had to come up with
actions at 10 times per second,
where it's acquiring a deep
understanding of the car
dynamics, "understanding"
in quotes,
but the ability to control a
car following racing lines,
precision racing maneuvers.
And when I say at the edge,
it means, if the car has--
the controller has to
figure out if it goes--
how fast it can go.
If it goes any faster,
it's going to spin out.
But if it goes any
slower, it's going
to be easy for a human to pass.
It's got to be right at that
edge of staying in control.
There's also tactics,
like I showed you
already the example
of defensive moves,
but there's many more
that I'll show you about.
And also there's this really
interesting and ill-defined
aspect of etiquette,
where you can't just
push another car off the track.
There's a human judge
that decides what's
sportsmanlike and
not, and the agent
has to have that
encoded as well.
So in this case, the
actions that the car used
were at 10 Hertz.
It could either control
the brake or the throttle
to be full backwards
or full forwards, can
turn full left or full right.
It's really already a factored
low-dimensional action space.
There's just two
dimensions to it.
So we don't have to go through
what we did with SLAC to try
to discover that.
The agent already has
this natural factored,
low-dimensional action space.
The rewards initially
are just how fast
it moves along the track.
And then we added that's mainly
the positive rewards and then
also penalties for the tire
slipping or going off the track
or hitting a wall.
And then there were initially
in the initial work,
we had not visual features.
We have a couple of
papers since then
where we have used visual
inputs to help the car control.
But in the initial
paper, we were
giving things like
the car's velocity,
acceleration, roll,
pitch, and yaw
load on the tires and position
along the track to help it.
The compute infrastructure
was really important.
But by doing this within
the Sony ecosystem,
we were able to partner with
Polyphony Digital and Sony
Interactive Entertainment
for the PlayStation group
to have access to a large
bank of PlayStations,
which we could then use in
a sort of an Actor-Critic
kind of scenario where we have
a lot of roll-up workers getting
data on what happens
when you take an action
and what state comes back.
And then we used--
and we store that data
in experience replay
buffer and then use an
Actor-Critic method based
on Soft Actor-Critic,
but introduced
a new algorithm called
quantile-regression, or QR-SAC,
Quantile-Regression
Soft Actor-Critic, to be
able to train the policy, which
is pi, that's what actions you
take, and the critic, which
is the value function, which
is basically an
estimate of how good it
is to be where you currently
are in the state that you're in.
And so here's a slide
of technical details
for people who are familiar
with reinforcement learning.
Don't worry if this
doesn't all speak to you.
But basically, QR-SAC was
learning, not just the average
or the mean value
of taking an action,
but the full distribution.
What's the likelihood of a
really bad thing happening
versus a really
good thing happening
when you take an action.
So it's learning a quantile or a
distributional RL value function
as it's called,
and was also using
N-step returns rather
than one-step returns
to improve its performance.
The numbers here
on the right are
the lap time in a
particular configuration
on a particular
track, and so smaller
is better if you can get around
the track in 114 seconds.
That's better than 115 seconds.
So it's about almost
one second improvement,
which is pretty huge in this
domain between the vanilla Soft
Actor-Critic and
our new algorithm.
And we also found the sweet
spot for how the N-step returns.
The details are in
the paper, and I
have talks that go into much
more detail on how QR-SAC works
and the neural net
training details.
But the bottom line
is that after an hour,
the car is able to move
forwards, not run into walls
or drive off the track,
but not very efficiently.
After four hours,
to move much more
smoothly, after eight
hours, pretty expertly.
And actually after a day,
although we can run it
for a week, it's really
at superhuman performance,
like a person can't control.
And it's hard to see, I
know, on online in Zoom,
but it's cutting the
corners just exactly right
in the optimal way and in
a way that a person can't
do any better.
And in fact, it does
better than almost
every person in the world.
We tracked it against after 4
hours, 8 hours, and 24 hours.
The blue here is a histogram of
the best 100-lap times reported
by people on a worldwide server.
And after 24 hours,
it's better than almost
all of the reported lap times.
And if you take the
average of a person,
the best person's
average is shown here
on the left and the distribution
of GT Sophy's times,
better than the second,
third, fourth, and fifth
and on par with the best
person in the world.
And that's just
on this one track.
On the other two tracks,
that's significantly better
than the best
person's average time.
And so that was the first step.
But in this domain, being
faster wasn't enough.
There were two other
challenges to solve.
Like I said, there's the race
car control, which I showed you
we could do, but there's also
the tactics and the etiquette.
So to be able to do--
to bring that, we
augmented the state space
to include knowledge of where
the other cars are nearby,
their relative
position, velocity,
and acceleration for the cars
in front and beyond and behind.
Also a reward for
passing, a penalty
for being passed
that encourages cars
to be a little more risky
when they're near other cars
to get around them.
And then importantly, we
had to curate the data.
This was another
one of innovations
so that the car gets the
experience that it needs.
So we put a bunch of
scenarios where it's just
racing on the empty track.
We can put 20 cars--
the important thing
to know is you
can put 20 cars on the
track at any one time
on a place in the
game, and so we
could put just 20 cars, spread
out around to get a lot of data.
But then we also
created some situations
where there's one car
behind one other car,
or one behind two or
one behind three or one
behind seven, so it gets
experience driving in traffic.
And in particular,
it gets experience
where it starts behind
another car on a straightaway
where it can--
it's encouraged to
but not explicitly
told to learn what's
known as a slipstream
pass, where it just
sort of like bicycle racing.
You draft behind the other
car so that you have lower air
resistance, and you can
get a lot of momentum
and then bounce out from behind
them and be able to pass them.
To be able to learn
that, it's important
that the simulator actually
models this slipstream effect
and it does.
And then also, where you start
behind another car in a corner,
so you learn these
sort of crossover
pass maneuvers, and also
a bunch of other tactics,
like what happens when you're in
a grid of the start of the car,
or if you've got this
particularly difficult parts
of the track.
And so one of the things
that was a key to the success
here was creating a carefully
engineered mix of data
in the experience replay
buffer so that various points
along the track, it
would be learning
from data from different
places, and then
create a mini batch for
training that gives the car
the right mix of experience.
And for the Nature paper, we
did this manually, but then
since then, we have worked
on automated methods
for coming up with the right
mix of data in this experience
replay buffer.
So some of the skills that
were learned by this agent
were things like that
slipstream pass where--
and these are narrated.
You can find some
talks online where
you hear the sound as well.
I don't have that
working right now,
but where the GT Sophy
is the colored car again.
It starts behind the other car,
gets in that low air resistance
mode, or your location
and is able to pass.
So that's an example
of that happening.
I already showed you
the defensive skill.
And here's a really
that double crossover,
where you're going to see
the two different cars--
the green and the gray,
I think, start out
behind the two human drivers.
But by the end of this turn,
they come out, both of them
in front of the human drivers.
And so you see on the right
the position or the line
that they took to be able to
successfully do that crossover
pass.
And again, this was not
programmed in or explicitly
rewarded in any way.
It was just part of
the overall learning
process and the experience
that we gave them.
And then finally, there was
this aspect of etiquette.
I'm not going to go into
the details either here,
but there's things like trying
to avoid avoidable collisions,
forcing a driver off the track,
doing things illegitimately
that are all sort
of judgment words.
Things that a
human Steward would
have to assess whether
they're happening or not.
But if you don't do
this, you'll end up
with aggressive agents
like the one shown here.
Here's also showing
the interface
of a person controlling the car.
But here's what you're
not allowed to do.
You can't just push a car
off the track like that.
But you also don't
want to be too timid.
So this was a clip where
GT Sophy was in front
and the human
announcer was saying,
there's no way that the person's
going to be able to pass.
It's a commanding lead.
But then GT Sophy
actually hit the brakes
because it was too
timid, it was too
concerned about
causing a collision,
and allowed the person to pass.
And so we needed to come up
with ways of mitigating that.
I think the human pass is
coming up right around here.
Right now, GT Sophy still in the
front, but I think you'll see--
yeah, here's Tomoaki
Yamanaka, the human expert,
now he has finally passed GT
Sophy because of that timidity.
So we added a bunch
of reward signals
to make sure the agent
wouldn't be too--
wouldn't get into
collisions and also
especially wouldn't
cause collisions
that it would be judged as being
at fault for and penalized for.
And so we did an
analysis in the paper
of how the different mix
of opponents and the reward
functions would lead
to different aspects
or different agents.
I'm running out of
time, so I'm not going--
I want to leave time for
plenty of time for questions.
So there's also an
important aspect here of,
we trained lots of
different agents,
but how do we choose
the one that's going
to go into the actual race.
That's an interesting aspect
that's covered in the paper.
But the bottom line is
that in July, the humans
outraced the people and
so we had a rematch.
And we analyzed what went wrong.
We spent a few
months improving it.
And by October created
a set of agents
that was able to finish
first and second place
in an eight-car race
for GT Sophy cars
against four humans in a
setting where you got points
based on 10 points for finishing
first, eight for second,
and then I think 7, 6
5, 4, 3 for the rest,
or something like that.
That was on the previous slide,
I think, what the scoring was.
Yeah, 10, 8, and 6 for the
first three places and then 5,
4, 3, 2, 1 for the other places,
and double points for the harder
start task.
But the bottom
line is by October,
we were able to finish first
and second in all the races.
And interestingly,
there were some quotes
from some of the drivers,
including Emily Jones.
I'm not going to play--
that's her there.
But saying things like,
I've learned something
from the agents.
I watched them, they're driving
differently than I would
and they've improved.
There are things
that I ought to try.
And now, like I
said earlier, this
has been permanently deployed
in the game in GT Sophy,
and there's been a lot of
testimonials from gamers
that this is a real big
addition to Gran Turismo,
and now it's out there on
many more cars and tracks.
But there's still a lot to do.
One of the things that we're
trying to get the agent
to drive with style.
So here's if we added a reward
for drifting the car, learned
to do something like
this to go around turns,
which is not something
any human driver would do,
but it sort of does
a little spin-move,
moving into a turn and
optimally comes out of it,
and also trying to
make it more fun.
That was an important part
of putting it into the game.
It wouldn't be fun
if you could just
race against an agent that can
outrace all of the best people.
At least if I were
playing the game,
I would see the agent just for
the first couple of seconds,
and then it would be gone
ahead of me for the rest.
So we needed to have a way to
make it also adjustable in terms
of its skill level.
So again, this was work of a
group of people at Sony AI.
And so I encourage you,
there are hour long talks
about this on my web page.
You can get the paper as well.
But that's mainly what I
wanted to show you today.
I know it's been a little
bit of a whirlwind.
But I wanted to--
one of the main things
I wanted to drive home
is that autonomous agents
research has been around
for a long time.
Agents are quite a general
thing in intelligent systems
that interact with the
environment through sensors.
Sorry, this is
getting gotten jumpy--
there we go-- through
sensors and effectors.
And then an intelligent,
complete agent
is one that has perception,
cognition, and action
from those sensors in between
the sensors and the actuators.
And that key components
of autonomous agents,
from my perspective, are
interaction and learning,
for sure, as I think
have been big themes
throughout your semester,
but also embodiment,
trying to get things
working on real robots.
And so with that,
I invite you to,
again, learn many more details
about all of the things
I mentioned today from my
web page, from publications.
If you look at my
teaching page, there's
a lot more online talks
that have, in some cases,
full one hour talks on things
I just mentioned for a minute
here.
But with that, I'll thank
you for your attention,
and be happy to take.